(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-09-05T21:37:06.240790",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.7-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
皆さーん、こんばんはー！ハロー！
Everyone, good evening! Hello!
こんばんはー！ / Selamat malam!
Good evening! / Good evening!
ということで、まず自己紹介からやっていきましょう！
So then, let's start off with self-introductions!
ホロライブの清楚担当、みんなのアイドルの夏色まつりです！
In charge of purity in hololive, everyone's idol, Natsuiro Matsuri here!
今日はMC、お願…頑張りまーす！
I'll be your MC today... I'll do my best!
じゃあ今日参加してくださる人たち、一人ずついきますよ。
Now then, let's introduce today's participants one by one.
じゃあ、ヨピピからお願いします！
First up, Iopipi, please go ahead!
はい！Iophoria, obisa! どうもです！ホロライブインドネシアからイオフィです！
Yes! Iophoria, obisa! Hello! Iofi from hololive Indonesia here!
今日はオノマトペをちょっと…
Today, onomatopoeia is something that...
えーっと、のことをちょっと勉強したいと思います！よろしくお願いします！
...um, I'd like to study a bit! Nice to meet you!
お願いしまーす！
Looking forward to it!
じゃあ、こぼちゃん！
Next, Kobo-chan!
Boba boba baka, Kobo Kanaeru at your service. Let me be your sun to shine your day.
えへん！こぼ・かなえる、レイン・シャーマンです！
*Ahem!* Kobo Kanaeru, rain shaman!
今日はオノマトペア、勝ちだ！
Today, onomatopoeia... victory is mine!
よろしくお願いします！がんばろー！
Nice to meet you! Let's do this!
じゃあ、続いてジジ！
Alright, next is Gigi!
こんばんはー！ジジです！
Good evening! I'm Gigi!
Team Green... えーっと、日本語ちょっと上手ない…
Team Green... um, my Japanese isn't very good...
オノマトペ、うーん、ちょっと日本語頑張って、頑張ります！
Onomatopoeia, um, I'll do my best with Japanese!
ありがとー！がんばれー！
Thank you! You can do it!
はい！じゃあ続いて、ほぼJPのベィちゃん！
Alright, next up, our practically-JP Bae-chan!
いやいや、What's up? 我らはカオス、ホロライブのハコス・ベールズです！
No no, what's up? I am Chaos, Hakos Baelz from hololive!
今日は翻訳担当でやりたいと思います！よろしくお願いします！
Today I'll be in charge of translating! Nice to meet you all!
お願いしまーす！
Looking forward to it!
Yes, Hakos Baelz, whoo!
じゃあ最後、ラオラ！
And finally, Raora!
こんにちはー！あ、ラオラ・パンテーラです！
Hello! Ah, I'm Raora Panthera!
今日はえっと、絵を描いたり日本語で話したり、頑張りましょう！
Today, let's do our best drawing and speaking Japanese!
はい、お願いしまーす！Ciao ciao!
Yes, let's do this! Ciao ciao!
はい、ということで本日はですね、皆さんにオノマトペクイズに答えてもらいます！
Alright, so today, you all will be answering an onomatopoeia quiz!
ちょっとね、日本独特の表現とかもたくさんあるんですが、頑張って答えてね。
There are lots of expressions unique to Japanese, but do your best to answer them, okay?
はい！ / うーん…
Okay! / Hmm...
ぜひね、日本に来る際はいっぱい使っていただきたいなと思います！
When you visit Japan, I really hope you use them a lot!
イェーイ！
Yay!
早速、第1問行きましょう！
Let's jump right into Question 1!
Oh, why? First question! Question one!
このオノマトペは何を表しているでしょうか？
What does this onomatopoeia represent?
コケコッコー
"Koke-kokko"
What's... the sound of... / コケコッコー / Cock-a-doodle-doo?
What's... the sound of... / Koke-kokko / Cock-a-doodle-doo?
Where do you hear this onomatopoeia from? Onomatopoeia...
あ、分からない！
Ah, I don't know!
Guess! / 分からない場合はどうします？
Guess! / What if we don't know?
あ、じゃあヒントは、動物の鳴き声ですね。
Ah, a hint is that it's an animal cry.
何の動物の鳴き声でしょう？ / It's an animal cry, what animal is it?
What animal's cry would this be? / It's an animal cry, what animal is it?
I don't know what to...
Can I draw, right?
I can draw, right?
なんかペンがおかしいんです、私の。何で？
Something's wrong with my pen. Why?
あら？
Oh dear?
ペンおかしい。あ、描けた。
The pen's weird. Ah, I can draw.
コケコッコー
Cock-a-doodle-doo~
けこけここっこー
けこかこけっこー
Cock-a-doodle-doo~
かわいい
Cute.
ペンがおかしい。あれ、何でこうなっちゃうの？
The pen is acting up. Huh, why is it doing this?
けこけここっこー
Cock-a-doodle-doo~
描けるかな？
Can I draw it?
けこけここっこー
Cock-a-doodle-doo~
あ、ちょっと待ってください。アプリ再起動します。すみません。
Ah, please wait a moment. I'll restart the app. Sorry.
うん、描ける？
Yeah, can you draw?
Sh- should we draw?
You can do whatever, like write or draw.
I just write it. Whatever.
I just wrote it. / Whatever.
I drew it cause I don't know what it is in Japanese!
It's all right.
I don't know the word!
あ、何で？ください、はい。
Ah, why? Please... okay.
描けるかな？
Can I draw it?
あ、描けます！ / あ、よかった！
Ah, I can draw! / Ah, great!
よかった。
That's a relief.
コケコッコー / ココー
Cock-a-doodle-doo / Co-co
声に出したらわかるかも。 / コケコッコー
Saying it out loud might help you figure it out. / Cock-a-doodle-doo
けここっこー
Cock-a-doodle-doo~
トイ！
Toy!
大丈夫かい？ / コケコッコー
You okay there? / Cock-a-doodle-doo
コケコッコー。コケコッコーですよ。
Cock-a-doodle-doo. It's cock-a-doodle-doo.
ココー
Co-co.
うーん。オッケー！じゃあ、1人ずつ聞いていきましょう！
Mm-hmm. Okay! Let's ask everyone one by one!
じゃあ、よぴぴ、何だと思いますか？ / はい！
First, Yopipi, what do you think it is? / Yes!
あ、チキンです！
Ah, chicken!
あ、チキン！はいはいはい。ニワトリね！ / チキンです！はい！
Ah, chicken! Right, right, a rooster! / It's chicken! Yes!
はい、じゃあ、えー、こぼちゃん！
Okay, next up, Kobo-chan!
Before I was thinking about frog, but I think "Kekokekko" is...
It's... it sounds like Indonesian "Kukuruyuk!"
So it's chicken!
おおー！なるほど！なるほどね！
Ooh! I see! That makes sense!
何か元々カエルだと思ってたんだけど、何かインドネシアのオノマトペでも...
I originally thought it was a frog, but in Indonesian onomatopoeia as well...
オノマ...オノマト...オノマトペ...
Onoma... Onomato... Onomatopoeia...
オノマトペ！オノマトペ！オノマトペ！
Onomatopoeia! Onomatopoeia! Onomatopoeia!
に、ニワトリの音に似てるので、チキン！ / 似てるね！チキン、なるほどー！
It sounds like a rooster, so chicken! / It does sound similar! Chicken, I see!
はい！じゃあ、ジジ！
Okay! Next, Gigi!
えー、けっけけきょここー、英語はCock-a-doodle-doo! チキンです！
Uh, Kekke Kekyokoko, in English it's Cock-a-doodle-doo! Chicken!
ふんふんふん、同じだね。じゃあ、ベータ！
Mhm mhm, same here. Then, Bae-ta!
あ、僕もニワトリ、チキンだと思います。
Ah, I also think it's a rooster, chicken.
はい、チキン。じゃあ、最後ラオラ！
Okay, chicken. Then last, Raora!
For me, it's like a bird that is screaming like "Koko!" like "I'm here!"
あ、コッコ？
Ah, koko?
'Cause you know he wants food in his mouth because maybe he's small, you know? I don't know.
うん、うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Wait, so what do you think it is? A bird?
Bird! さ、叫ぶ鳥！
Bird! S- Screaming bird!
叫ぶ鳥！叫ぶ鳥ね！鳥の、叫ぶ鳥ね！オッケー！
A screaming bird! Screaming bird! A bird... a screaming bird, okay!
なんかお腹空いてる叫ぶ鳥ね！
Like a hungry screaming bird, right!
了解！
Understood!
じゃあ、正解いきましょう！正解は...
Then let's see the correct answer! The answer is...
チキン！ニワトリでしたー！
Chicken! It was a rooster!
イエーイ！やったー！
Yay! Woohoo!
ラオラ... / まあ、正解にしますか！叫ぶ鳥だもんね！
Raora... / Well, shall we count it as correct? It is a screaming bird!
鳥！鳥は鳥だから！同じ同じ！ / 鳥は鳥だからね！素晴らしい！
Bird! A bird is a bird! Same thing! / A bird is a bird after all! Wonderful!
Everybody gets a point! Yay!
けこけかここ！ / コケコッコーでしたー！
Cock-a-doodle-doo! / It was cock-a-doodle-doo!
コケコッコー / けけこっこー
Cock-a-doodle-doo~ / Cock-a-doodle-doo~
はい、じゃあ続いて、第2問！こちらも動物の鳴き声でございます。
All right, moving on to Question 2! This is also an animal sound.
The second question is also the sound of an animal. / うん。
The second question is also the sound of an animal. / Yeah.
じゃあ、第2問こちら！「ケロケロ」
Then, here is Question 2! "Kero kero"!
ああー！ケロケロー！
Aaah! Kero kero!
Easy! Easy, easy! / Easy, easy! ケロケロ。
Easy! Easy, easy! / Easy, easy! Ribbit, ribbit.
あ、あ、え、え...
Ah, ah, eh, eh...
描けるかな？ / あ、え？え？
Can I draw it? / Ah... huh? Huh?
べっちゃん、それは...
Bae-chan, that is...
ええ？え？すごい！
Huh? What? Amazing!
何？何、何、何？
What? What, what, what?
まあ...
Well...
Eh, my pen... Okay, it works.
ケロケロケロケロケロケロケロケロ
Ribbit ribbit ribbit ribbit ribbit ribbit ribbit ribbit
ケロケロ
Ribbit ribbit
うん、かわいい。描けるかな？
Yeah, cute. Can you draw it?
ラオラ、大丈夫？
Raora, are you okay?
あ、だ、大丈夫、オッケー。Okay, it's working. Thank you.
Ah, I'm- I'm okay, okay. Okay, it's working. Thank you.
べっちゃんのは何？え？え？
What is Bae-chan's? Huh? Huh?
Wait, hold on, I forgot what it looked like!
Is that an owl? / What are you drawing?
Why is she drawing herself?
I forgot what it looked like!
画伯...
Quite the artist...
It's like a chimera, you know? キメラみたいよ。
It's like a chimera, you know? It's like a chimera.
キメラ？
A chimera?
キマイラをやめて。
Stop making chimeras.
おい、じゃあ、ちょっと一人ずつまた聞いていきますか？
All right, then, shall I go ask each of you again?
かわいい、みんな。
Everyone's drawings are so cute.
えー、じゃあ、ヨピピ。
Uh, let's start with Yopipi.
はい！
Yes!
カエルです。frogです。
It's a frog. Frog.
あー、frog、ケロ、ケロケロでしょ？
Ah, frog. "Kero," "Kero-kero," right?
うんうんうん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
なるほど。
I see.
はい！はい！
Yes! Yes!
じゃあ、続いてこぼちゃん。
All right, next is Kobo-chan.
私も、かえ…カエル？カエル、frog。frog、カエル。はい、ケロケロ。
Me too, fr... frog? Frog, frog. Frog, frog, yes. "Kero-kero."
漢字で書いてる！
You wrote it in kanji!
すごーい！
Amazing!
おー！わー！
Ooh! Wow!
まつりも書けないよ、カエル。
Even Matsuri can't write that kanji for frog.
はい、じゃあ続いてジジ。
All right, next is Gigi.
はい！
Yes!
ケロケロ、けろっぴ！
Kero-kero, Keroppi!
あ、ケロッ、ケロ、けろっぴ。おお！
Ah, Kero, kero, Keroppi. Oh!
はーい。
Yeah.
なるほど。
I see.
じゃあ、べーちゃん。
All right, Bae-chan.
あ、カエルです。
Ah, it's a frog.
お？カエルかな？
Oh? Is that a frog?
カエルです。
It's a frog.
カエルです？色んなカエルがいるから…
It's a frog? There are all kinds of frogs, but...
カエル…？カエル！
Frog...? Frog!
一瞬ちょっとね…
For a second, it kind of...
一瞬ネズミに見えたんだけどね。
It looked like a mouse for a second, but...
いやー、ちょっと…最近ね、カエル見てないんで…
Well, you see... I haven't seen a frog lately, so...
はい、一応カエル。画伯だ。
Yes, a frog for now. You're quite the artist.
その隣の…ラオラ、めっちゃ絵上手い！
Next to her... Raora, your drawing is super good!
かわいい！
Cute!
イェーイ！
Yay!
はい、カエルですね？
All right, it's a frog, right?
うん。
Yeah.
カエルです。
It's a frog.
はい！
All right!
じゃあ「ケロケロ」、正解は…
Then, for "Kero-kero," the correct answer is...
「カエル」でございます！
"Frog"!
正解ー！やったー！
Correct! Yay!
Easy, easy, easy, easy!
日本語上手！
Your Japanese is so good!
日本語上手よー。ねー。
Everyone's Japanese is so good. Yeah.
日本語上手。
So good at Japanese.
じゃあ続いていきますよ。
All right, moving on.
続いては、こちら。
Next up is this one.
馬の鳴き声は、日本だと何というでしょう？
What sound does a horse make in Japanese?
What sound does a horse make?
ホース？
Horse?
Japanese onomatopoeia.
分からなーい！
I don't know!
何て聞こえるかな？何て聞こえるかな？
What does it sound like to you? What does it sound like?
うーーー！
Ooooh!
うー、みみ…
Ugh, my ears...
イメージ、イメージして。
Imagine it, just imagine.
It's all right, JJ. Feel it from your heart.
You can do it!
一人ずつ鳴いてもらうからね。
I'll have each of you make the sound, okay?
She's gonna ask each of you to sound out the onomatopoeia that you have come up with.
オッケー？オッケー、オッケー。
Okay? Okay, okay.
ジジ、しんどい？
Gigi, is it tough?
じゃあ、一人ずつ鳴いてもらいますか。
All right, shall we have everyone make the sound one by one?
じゃあヨピピから。ヨピピの馬の鳴き声…
Let's start with Yopipi. Yopipi's horse sound...
お願いします。どうぞ！
Please go ahead!
「はりきっていこう！」です。
It's "Let's go enthusiastically!".
「はりきっていこう」？！それ喋ってない？！
"Let's go enthusiastically"?! Isn't that talking?!
I don't think she says that.
そうやって鳴くの？
Does it make a sound like that?
だって馬これしかないんですよ！
Because this is the only horse thing I know!
ウマ娘すぎる！
Too much Uma Musume!
馬これしか知らないですよ！
That's all I know about horses!
じゃあ続いて、えー、こぼちゃん。
All right, next is Kobo-chan.
あー、「ひーふー、ひーふー」。
Ah... "Hee-hoo, hee-hoo."
ああ、「ひーふー、ひーふー」。
Ah, "Hee-hoo, hee-hoo."
「ひふひふ」？
"Hee-foo, hee-foo"?
I feel like that's a different sound.
それ、別じゃない？
Wait, isn't that breathing?
別の呼吸じゃん！
That's breathing!
「ひーふー、ひーふー」
"Hee-hoo, hee-hoo."
オッケー、オッケー、「ひーふー、ひーふー」ね。
Okay, okay, "Hee-hoo, hee-hoo."
じゃあ続いてジジ。
All right, next is Gigi.
Wild horse!
リアル！
So realistic!
じゃあ続いてべーちゃん。
All right, next is Bae-chan.
えっと…
Um...
「うまーー！」
"UMAAA--!"
めっちゃ日本語喋るやん！
It speaks total Japanese!
お前がねーよ。
No way.
じゃあ続いて、えー、ラオラ。
All right, next is Raora.
Okay, uh... maybe something like...
おお！リアル！
Oh! Realistic!
Turning into a horse!
You're a cat!
めっちゃ似てた！
That sounded just like one!
Why are you sounding like a horse?
Maybe I'm both.
正解は…
The correct answer is...
馬の鳴き声って何？「ヒヒーン」でした！
What is a horse's sound? It was "Hihiin"!
ひひー？
"Hihii"?
ヒヒーン？
"Hihiin"?
Yes, yes, yes.
じゃあ一番近かったのラオラじゃないの？
Then wasn't Raora the closest?
ラオラはリアルすぎたな。
Raora's was too realistic.
リアルすぎた。
Too realistic.
ラオラ…
Raora...
「ひひーん」か。
"Hihiin," huh.
Oh, there's an "N" at the end.
「ヒ・ヒ・ー・ン」
"Hi-hi-i-n."
Why do horses make that sound?
Sound like Michael Jackson.
Hee-hee!
Kobo has "hihu" too.
Does it... am I count?
Oh yeah, Kobo does!
Ah "hihu", I have "hihu" too.
I have "hihu" too.
No "hihu"?
No "hihu", no.
"hu" no? No "hihu"?
No "hu"? No "hihu"?
So it's no counting.
No count. No count, sorry.
「ひーふーひーふー」可愛いけどね。
"Hee-hoo hee-hoo..." It's cute, but...
はい、残念ながら不正解でございます。
Yes, unfortunately that is incorrect.
では続いて、今から言う言葉の意味をね、
Alright, moving on, for this next word,
当ててください。じゃあ、行きます。
please guess what it means. Here we go!
[ぺこぺこだ～！の意味は？]
[What is the meaning of "Pekopeko da~!"?]
「ぺこぺこだ～！」
"Pekopeko da~!"
の意味は... ああ、はいはいはい。
The meaning of... Ah, right, right!
What does pekopeko mean?
ぺこぺこ...
Pekopeko...
おお、みんなスラスラと書いてくれている。
Ooh, everyone's writing smoothly!
ぺこぺこ、ぺこぺこ...
Pekopeko, pekopeko...
「ぺこぺこだ。」「ぺこぺこだ～！」
"Pekopeko da." "Pekopeko da~!"
ぺこぺこだ～
Pekopeko da~
オッケーかな？オッケーかな？
Are you all ready? Ready?
可愛いイラストが描かれている。
There are cute drawings being drawn!
じゃあ聞いていきますか。じゃあ、よっぴー！
Shall we ask everyone? First, Yoppi!
はい！ハングリーです！食べたいです、プリン食べたいです！
Yes! It's "hungry"! I want to eat pudding!
食べたい！ハングリー。
I want to eat! Hungry.
食べたいです、オッケー。こぼちゃんはこれです。ぺこぺこ。
"Want to eat," okay. Kobo-chan has this: pekopeko.
じゃあ、こぼちゃん！
Alright, Kobo-chan!
はい！ぺこぺこインドネシア語意味は「lapar」です！
Yes! Pekopeko in Indonesian means "lapar"!
「Lapar」はどういう意味ですか、よっぴー先生？
What does "lapar" mean, Yoppi-sensei?
「Lapar」は「hungry」。
"Lapar" is "hungry."
ああ、hungry！hungryね、オッケー。
Ah, hungry! Hungry, okay.
じゃあ、ジジ！ジジ顔だけしか描いてない。
Next, Gigi! Gigi only drew a face!
ジジ？
Gigi?
お腹すいた～！ぺこぺこ～！
I'm hungry! Pekopeko~!
お腹すいたね。ジジ可愛い～
"I'm hungry," yes. Gigi is so cute!
じゃあ、続いてべーちゃん！
Alright, next is Bae-chan!
はい、ハングリーです。腹減った。/ 腹減った、オッケー。
Yes, "hungry." Hara hetta. / Hara hetta, okay.
じゃあ、ラオラ！
Next, Raora!
Very hungry!
ああ～じゃあ全員同じだね！全員ハングリー。
Ah~ so everyone has the same answer! All hungry!
可愛い。はい、ハングリー、ハングリー。
So cute! Yes, hungry, hungry.
えー、ということで... 全員正解～！
Which means... everyone is correct~!
Yay~!
Easy easy! 上手上手！
Easy, easy! Good job, good job!
はい、じゃあ続いての意味を当ててくださいね。
Alright, guess the meaning for the next one too!
Next one is also guess the meaning. / じゃあ、行きます。
Next one is also guess the meaning. / Here we go!
「チンしてね！」
"Chin shite ne!"
は？おお！
Huh? Oh!
「チンしてね。」/「チンしてね！」
"Chin shite ne." / "Chin shite ne!"
「チンしてね」...何だろう？
"Chin shite ne"... I wonder what that is?
「チンしてね！」/「チンしてね。」
"Chin shite ne!" / "Chin shite ne."
可愛い、可愛い、可愛い。「チンしてね？」
So cute, so cute! "Chin shite ne?"
うう～「チンしてね？」
Uu~ "chin shite ne?"
「チンしてね。」チン...
"Chin shite ne." Chin...
分かるかな？声に出したら分かるかもよ。チン...
I wonder if they know? Maybe if you say it out loud?
チンって...
What is "chin"...?
可愛い。これ...これじゃないの？
So cute! Isn't it this...?
チン...
Chin...
オッケーかな？
Are you ready?
こぼちゃん、ちょっと下に...
Kobo-chan is drawing underneath...
はい、じゃあ聞きますか。よっぴーどうでしょう？
Alright, let's ask! Yoppi, what do you think?
はい！最初はちょっとドアのベルだったんだけど、
Yes! At first I thought of a doorbell,
あれピンポンだから、チンしたらあのマイクロウェーブ？
but that's "ding-dong", so "chin" is a microwave?
ああ、マイクロウェーブ！温める...電子レンジ。
Ah, microwave! To heat up... microwave oven.
電子レンジ終わったら「チン！」って鳴るじゃない。/ なるほど！
When it finishes, it goes "chin!", right? / I see!
じゃあ、こぼちゃんは... あれ？あれ？こぼちゃん？！
Now then, Kobo-chan is... wait? Kobo-chan?!
こぼちゃん、これは...？ / なんか、チンは... ちょっと...
Kobo-chan, what is this...? / Well, "chin" is...
いやいやいやいや！Danger! Dangerous!
No no no no! Danger! Dangerous!
そのものみたい！そのものみたい！
It looks like that thing! Like that itself!
ああ、そのチンは... あら～「Pee please」ね。
Ah, that "chin"... Oh dear... "Pee please", huh.
「Chin please...」チン＝トイレ？！
"Chin please..." Chin = toilet?!
多分...
Maybe...
分かんない！
I don't know!
なるほど。じゃあ次行きますか。Gigi、Gigi。
I see. Alright, should we move to the next person? Gigi, Gigi.
分からない... It's...
I don't know... It's...
Uh, chin-yabai!
チンやばい？！
Chin-yabai?!
Chin-yabai!
ノーヤバい！
No yabai!
やばくない、もう！
It's really not yabai!
じゃあ、Baeちゃん、Baeちゃんお願いします。
Okay, Bae-chan, Bae-chan, go ahead please!
はい、レンジのチンですね。で、温めてねっていうことで、
Yes, it's the \"ding\" from a microwave, meaning to warm something up,
Please go and warm it up in the microwave.
うん、はいはいはい。
Yeah, right, right.
じゃあ最後、Raora！
Alright, and last is Raora!
えー、分からない... 分からない！
Um, I don't know... I don't know!
分かんない？どうしよっか。- Maybe... - Maybe?
I don't know. What should we do? - Maybe... - Maybe?
Maybe something like, uh...
Maybe when, when the glass, when you touch the glass?
Maybe when the glass... when you touch the glass?
ああ、ガラス！乾杯？グラス？
Oh, a glass! A toast? Clinking glasses?
「チン」って言うかも。- 確かに。はいはいはい。
It might make a "chin" sound. - True, true.
Not yabai.
No, ノーヤバいね。- ノーヤバい。- Not yabai.
No, "no yabai", right? - No yabai. - Not yabai.
もう分かんないよ！- はい、分かんないね。
Well, I don't know! - Yes, she didn't know.
じゃあ、こちらはですね、正解は... えー、microwave。チン。
Well, as for this one, the correct answer is... a microwave! "Chin!"
ご飯を温めてくださいっていう...
It means "please warm up the food."
電子レンジで！- そっかー！
With a microwave! - Ah, is that so...
If you want to warm up food in a microwave, you'd be like, "チンしてね。"
If you want to warm up food in a microwave, you'd be like, "Chin shite ne."
「チンしてね」。ああ、なるほど。
"Chin shite ne." Ah, I see.
例えば、ご飯をこう置いといて、
For example, you leave food out like this,
あとに帰ってきた人、ご飯が冷めちゃってるから「チンしてね」ってメモを残したりしますね。
and for someone coming home later, since the food is cold, you'd leave a note saying "Chin shite ne."
おおー！なるほど！
Oh! I see!
Kobo、「チンしてね」。「チンして...」
Kobo, "Chin shite ne." "Chin shite..."
Like, "Please warm it up for me." チンしてね。
Like, "Please warm it up for me." "Chin shite ne."
Oh, okay! So if you wanna, if you wanna say pee, please...
Oh, okay! So if you wanna say "pee, please"...
Yeah, how do you say that? I might need that one.
No pee!
No, no pee!
じゃあ、じゃあpeeはどう言ったらいいの？
Then how should you say pee?
Peeってあれ... - Pee please?
Like "pee"? - "Pee please?"
オノマトペは、Pee please!
An onomatopoeia! "Pee please!"
Peeってさ、おしっこ？
Wait, isn't "pee" pee-pee?
おしっこ。- おしっこ？
Oshikko. - Oshikko?
あ、じゃあ「シー」とかね、「シー」「シャー」とか。
Ah, then "shii" or "shaa" maybe.
Shaa please!
「シャー」「シー」、なるほど！
"Shaa", "shii", I see!
はい、「シャー」「シー」とか... うん。
Right, "shaa-shii" or something...
シャーお願い！
"Shaa please!"
No, no, no! No, ダメね！ダメダメよ！
No, no, no! No, that's not good! That's bad, bad!
すみません、シャーお願い！
Excuse me, "shaa please!"
ダメダメダメ！ダメー！
No! No! No!
危険な日本語教えちゃった！
We taught them dangerous Japanese!
ありがとうございます！分かりました！
Thank you very much, I understand now!
やべえ！
Oh shoot!
えー、じゃあnext行きましょう。こちらでございます。
Well then, let's move on to the next one. Here it is.
「静まり返ったとき」、めっちゃ静かなとき、
"When everything falls silent" - when it's super quiet,
使うオノマトペは何でしょうか？
what onomatopoeia do you use?
What's the onomatopoeia that they use when it goes really quiet?
Oh, maybe I remember.
あ、何だっけ？静かなとき...
What was it? When it's quiet...
What that mean?
Like when it goes really quiet all of a sudden,
When it goes really quiet all of a sudden,
what's the onomatopoeia that they would use?
You can write it in Romaji, or you can just sound it out.
I'm gonna write the onomatopoeia I just learned!
漫画読んだら分かるかもね。漫画に書いてあることもあるかも。
You might know it if you read manga. It's often written in manga.
Japanese manga.
Might be in manga that you've read before.
What is it, like that? Is that how you spell it?
I don't know if it's valid.
まあまあいいでしょう！
Well, that's fine I guess!
何何何？- いやいやいや。
What, what, what? - No, no, no.
じゃあ聞いていきますね。Yopi-piから。
Alright, let's ask around. Starting with Yopi-pi.
はい、「しーーん」です。
Yes, it's "Shiiin".
はい、「シーン」ね。はいはいはい。
Yes, "shiin", right! Okay, okay.
続いてKoboちゃん。
Next up, Kobo-chan.
しーー。
"Shiii".
「しー」、はいはい。
"Shii", okay, okay.
じゃあ、Gigi！
Okay, Gigi!
シャー！
"Shaa!"
シャー？
"Shaa"?
Isn't that the pee? - No...
Well, wouldn't it get quiet after you pee?
Get quiet after you pee?
Oh...
じゃ、続いて Baeちゃん。
Well, next up, Bae-chan.
いやー、忘れた。なんか、「すん」？
No, I forgot. Like, "sun"?
あー、「すん」？
Ah, "sun"?
違う。
Wrong.
「すん」はちょっと違うか。
"Sun" is a bit off, isn't it?
「しーん」だったか？
Was it "shiin"?
いやどっちかと思ってたんだよねー。
I was wondering which one of the two it was.
なるほど、なるほど。
I see, I see.
Oh, me?
うん、yes.
Yeah, yes.
Oh, uh, yeah, I think it's "shiin".
Like, I remember when I read some mangas...
I might be wrong...
Maybe it's "shin".
うんうんうん、しーん。オッケー。マンガにな。オッケー、got it, got it. オッケー。
Yeah yeah yeah, "shiin". Okay. In manga, right. Okay, got it, got it. Okay.
じゃ、正解に行きましょう。
Well, let's look at the answer.
正解は...「しーーん」でございます。
The answer is... "Shiiiin"!
やっぱり！
I knew it!
ということでRaoraが正解だね。
So Raora got it right.
You were so close, Gigi, you were so close!
You were so close.
Gigiのは「しーん」
Gigi's was "shin".
Gigi, you was close! "Shin", "shin".
Gigi, you were so close! "Shin", "shin".
そう、しー...あ、Nが必要ですね、こぼちゃん。し・ん。ね。
Right, shi... Ah, you need an "n", Kobo-chan. Shi-n. Right?
あー！そうですね！
Ah! That's right!
Lalalalala...
惜しい！まあまあまあ、はいはいはい。
Close! Well, well, okay okay.
Very close. Good enough.
まあまあまあ。Gigiは絶対に違うからね。
Well, Gigi is definitely wrong though.
「しゃー」って、おしっこじゃないですか、「しゃー」って。
Isn't "shaa" like peeing? "Shaa"!
そう、さっきの「ピー」の音...
Yeah, the "pee" sound earlier...
一応なんか理屈的にも間違ってないと思うんすけどね。
I mean logically I think I wasn't wrong though.
え？
Huh?
なんかGigiがさ、立っておしっこした後にさ、静かになるじゃん。
Like after Gigi stands and pees, it gets quiet, right?
あ、そうそう、さっき言って...
Ah, yeah yeah, what you said earlier...
だから「しゃー」
That's why "shaa".
ちょっと違うけどね。
That's a bit different though.
I was explaining your logic.
Oh okay, thank you. So you're defending me.
Yeah, I was defending you.
I got you, I got you.
はい、じゃあ続いていきましょう。
All right, let's move on to the next one.
続いて、えー、とっても冷たい飲み物を表すオノマトペは何でしょうか？
Next, what is the onomatopoeia representing an extremely cold drink?
Oh, what's the sound of an extremely cold drink?
飲み物？
Drink?
そう、drink。
Yes, drink.
えーー！
Ehhh!
あ、あれとあれだけど...
Ah, it's either that or that, but...
何々に冷えたって言いますね。
We say it's chilled to [blank].
あれでしょう。
It's that one.
Cold drink?
I only have one word in my head again!
Cold drink... Cold drink...
これもね、マンガに出てくるかもね。
This might appear in manga too.
Maybe manga. Aha aha.
分からない！
I don't know!
イメージ、イメージ。
Image, image.
Image, or sound? If I guess wrong, goodbye!
What do you have in mind?
Just do it! Just do it!
I'm scared! No!
It's okay!
Gigiがなんかヤバそうなやつが考え...そうだね。
Gigi seems to be thinking of something crazy... indeed.
な、何を言おうとしてるの、Gigi、大丈夫？
W-What are you trying to write, Gigi, are you okay?
Gigi大丈夫？大丈夫。
Is Gigi okay? I'm okay.
大丈夫、大丈夫。大丈夫、大丈夫。
You're okay, you're okay. Okay, okay.
でもあれかな、ビールとかに結構言うかな？
But you know, is it often used for beer?
Ah, you use it with beer?
オッケー？
Okay?
じゃ、いきますか。えー、じゃあイオフィぴ。
Well, shall we go? Alright, then Iofi-pi.
はい！確か、「キンキン」なんとかのほにゃららです。はい。
Yes! If I recall, it's "kin-kin" something something. Yes.
えっと、この前スタジオで誰かさん、ホロメンの誰かさんがマネージャーに「キンキンの飲み物欲しいです」って言われた。
Um, the other day at the studio, someone—a Holomem—told the manager "I want a kin-kin cold drink."
おー！なるほどー！
Ooh! I see!
そうそうそう。ちょうど夏のぐらいで、うん、誰かさん...ちょっと忘れちゃったんだけど、スタジオでなんか聞いたことがあります。
Right right right. It was around summer, and yeah, someone... I forgot who, but I heard it at the studio.
ほー。「キンキン」ね。オッケー。はい、じゃあこぼ。
Ho~. "Kin-kin", right. Okay. Next, Kobo.
Ah, so I thought like when you... after you drink cold, a really cold drink, your...
After that, your head will hurt and then you will say "atata".
ああーー！
Aahh!
なんか冷たいもの飲んだ後さ、頭痛くなるんじゃないですか。
Like after you drink something cold, your head hurts, right?
ああ、なるほど。その時に「あたたたたた」
Ah, I see. At that time, "atatatatata".
なるほどね、はい。
I see, yes.
だからこそ「あたたた」って答えました。
That's why I answered "atatata".
あたたた。オッケー、オッケー。
Atatata. Okay, okay.
はいはい。じゃあ続いて Gigi。
Okay, okay. Next is Gigi.
うーん、えっ...
Umm, uh...
Send it, send it, send it... Ahh, mm?
寒い！
Cold!
寒い？
Cold?
寒いね？寒い。
Cold, huh? Cold.
Yes. Yes.
寒い？
Cold?
寒い、うまい。
Cold, tasty.
寒い、うまい？かわいい。
Cold, tasty? Cute.
オッケー。寒い。寒い飲み物、オッケー。
Okay. Cold. Cold drink, okay.
はい
Okay.
はい、OK。
Yes, okay.
かわいい！
So cute!
じゃあ続いて、べーちゃん。
Alright, next up is Bae-chan.
なんか「き」から始まった気がした。
I feel like it started with "ki".
でも忘れた。
But I forgot.
「き」から始まる。「きー」なんちゃらかんちゃら「きー」...
It starts with "ki". "Kee-" something something "kee-"...
「き」「き」...
"Ki," "ki"...
「き」「きん」で...
"Ki," "kin"...
あ、「き」！「きー」OK！
Ah, "ki"! "Kee-", okay!
OK、OK、OK。「きー」
Okay, okay, okay. "Kee-".
じゃあ、ラオーラ。
Next, Raora.
あ、あ、えーっと... かんぱーい！
Ah, uh, it's... Cheers!
あ、かんぱい！
Ah, cheers!
かんぱーい！
Cheers!
That's right, let's go. OK.
That's right, let's go. Okay.
Kanpai!
Cheers!
じゃあ、正解いきましょう。正解は...
Alright, let's reveal the answer. The answer is...
キンキンに冷えた飲み物でございますので、
Since it's a freezing cold drink,
「キンキン」ですね！
it's "kin-kin"!
イェーイ！すごい！
Yay! Amazing!
やったー！ありがとう誰かさん、ホロ便の。
Yay! Thank you, whoever said it in HoloBen.
ね、誰かさんありがとうございます。
Yeah, thank you, whoever you are.
キンキンかー。
"Kin-kin," huh.
はい、キンキンに。
Yes, kin-kin.
キンキンねー。
Kin-kin, right.
「キンキンに冷えてやがるよ」っていうセリフがアニメにもありますね。
There's that famous line in anime: "It's freezing cold!"
ほっほー。
I see.
はい。じゃあ続いては... えっーと、いきますか。続いてこちら。
Yes. Moving on to the next one... shall we? Here's the next one.
きらきら。星がきらきらしてるみたいな、
"Kira-kira." Like how stars sparkle,
きらきらのもっと強い表現。もっときらきら。
a stronger expression for "kira-kira." Even more sparkly.
おー！もっと眩しい？
Oh! Even more dazzling?
ほーほーほー。どう表現するでしょうか？
Hoo hoo hoo. How would you express that?
So how would you describe something that, you know, you have "kira-kira" to describe something that's sparkling, something that's even more bright and shiny?
More than "kira-kira".
あれ？これじゃないの？
Huh? Isn't it this?
これは結構何パターンかある。
There are actually a few different variations of this.
There's a couple of different variations.
There are a couple of different variations.
なんかあの、ほにゃららの、えっと、ポケモンを思い出しちゃって...
I kind of remembered that, uh, Pokemon...
ポケモン！
Pokemon!
ポケモン？
Pokemon?
So, so like "kira-kira", but...
A more stronger... yeah, like more... With more punch.
A stronger... yeah, like more... With more punch.
More power. With more punch.
Level up "kira-kira".
Level up "kira-kira". Powerful "kira-kira".
きらきら... きらきらぁ...
Kira-kira... kira-kiraa...
きらきら...
Kira-kira...
分かるかな？
Can you guess it?
かわいい。
Cute.
こんなだろう...
It's probably something like this...
そうそうそうそう...
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah...
はい、はい、はい、はい。
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
書いてくれてる、まつりを。
They're drawing me!
かわいい。
Cute.
どうでしょう？
How's this?
I'm bribing the judge.
はい。
Yes.
What?
I'm bribing the judge.
She's trying to bribe the judge. Bribing the judge!
Why?
I don't know the word!
なんかMCさんに賄賂送ってます。
Looks like they're bribing the MC.
おっ、ほーほー。
Oh, ho-ho.
何何？
What's this?
あの、知らないので、あの、MCに賄賂してます。
Um, since I don't know, um, I'm bribing the MC.
賄賂？！
A bribe?!
あー、そういうこと？じゃあヒントね、ヒント。
Ah, is that it? Here's a hint then.
ヒントは、ホロライブメンバーの曲の歌詞に入ってますね。
The hint is, it's in the lyrics of a Hololive member's song.
Oh, it's in the lyrics of a Hololive member's song!
もっと言うと、ねねちの、あの曲
More specifically, that song by Nenechi
Nenechi's song!
に、入ってる。
contains it.
あとは、「きらきら」の進化。
Also, it's an evolution of "kira-kira."
「きらきら」をパワーアップさせた感じかな？
Like a powered-up version of "kira-kira"?
おーー！
Ohhh!
が、ヒント。どうでしょうか？
That's the hint. How about it?
分かるかな？
Can you figure it out?
Okay, 賄賂、OK？
Okay, is the bribe okay?
賄賂は...
The bribe...
え、これ賄賂くれたの誰？誰がくれたの？
Wait, who gave this bribe? Who gave it?
Gigi. / ラオーラ？
Gigi. / Raora?
Gigi? Gigi, Gigi, Gigi?
あ、Gigiじゃあ、賄賂として、あの、
Ah, Gigi, then as your bribe, um...
Very cute voice please, まつりお姉ちゃん、OK？
In a very cute voice please, say "Matsuri Big Sis", okay?
あの、あの絵が賄賂の話よ。
Um, that drawing was the bribe!
あ、そういう？！
Ah, that was it?!
えー、きらきら、え、え、まつりお姉さん、きらきら！
Um, sparkly... um, um, Matsuri Big Sis, sparkly!
大好き！
I love you!
おっほー！ｷﾀ━━━━(ﾟ∀ﾟ)━━━━!!
Oh-ho! Yessss!!
ご馳走様でした。やば。
Thanks for the treat. Oh man.
かわいいー！
So cute!
あ、Gigi、あの、Your name word, ヒントね、Your name word.
Ah, Gigi, a word with your name in it is a hint! A word with your name.
Your name is in it? My name is a hint?!
Hint, it is.
あー、あれね！
Ah, that one!
で、えー、ねねちの曲にも入ってるよ、と。
And it's also in Nenechi's song.
オッケー？
Okay?
いけるかな？
Are you ready?
Okay.
じゃあ聞いてこ。
Let's hear them then.
じゃ、よぴぴから。
Alright, starting with Yopipi.
はーい。えっと、きらん... なんかそのキラッキラとかのそういうの
Okay. Um, "kiran"... or something like "kirakkira",
うん、うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
かなーと思ってて
is what I was thinking,
きらん
"Kiran."
でも今思ってたらあれだなと思ってて。
but now that I think about it, maybe not.
お、変えますか？
Oh, do you want to change it?
きらん...
"Kiran..."
あ、いや、大丈夫です。
Ah, no, it's fine.
でもなんか、そう、なんか
But like, yeah, like,
そのキラッキラもっと強いのが、なんかいつも太陽？
something stronger than "kirakkira", like the sun?
うん、うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
太陽、なんか、あ、太陽ピカーン！ってなっちゃうじゃないですか。
The sun, like, the sun goes "Pikaaan!", right?
うん、うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
太陽によく使われるものかな？
Is it something often used for the sun?
なるほど。
I see.
はい、はい、はい、はい。
Right, right, right.
じゃあ、こぼちゃん。
Next, Kobo-chan.
可愛く言ってみて。
Say it cutely.
可愛く！
Cutely!
Cuz I heard someone saying...
'Cause I heard someone saying...
Pokemon?
So, I think like...
Pika Pika!
めっちゃ言うやん！
She really went for it!
Uh-huh.
ピカピカね。
Pika pika, I see.
オッケー。
Okay.
確かに強い！
That's definitely strong!
確かに強い、ピカピカは。
Indeed, pika pika is strong.
確かに。ピカピカ強い。
True. Pika pika is strong.
で、ストロング... ストロングピカピカ！
And strong... Strong Pika Pika!
うん。
Yeah.
じゃあ、続いてジジ。
Alright, next up is Gigi.
GG muri...
きらきら？
Kirakira?
ギラギラ！
Gira gira!
はー、はいはい。ギラギラ。オッケー。
Ah, okay, okay. Gira gira. Okay.
オッケーオッケー。じゃあべーちゃんいきましょう。
Okay, okay. Alright, let's go with Bae-chan.
あ、僕もピカピカだと思った。
Ah, I thought it was pika pika too.
はい。ピカピカね。
Right. Pika pika.
ピカピカ。
Pika pika.
おー。
Ohh.
えー、じゃあ、ラオーラ。
Hmm, next, Raora.
Same for me. I heard about Pokemon.
I thought about Pika Pika too.
動きもいいとこあるね。
The movements are great too.
なるほど、なるほど。
I see, I see.
ポケモンヒント
Pokemon hint.
オッケー。じゃあ正解いきましょう。
Okay. Let's reveal the correct answer.
正解は...
The correct answer is...
「ギラギラ」でジジ正解！
"Gira gira", so Gigi is correct!
ギラギラ？天才！
Gira gira? Genius!
天才じゃん！
You're a genius!
天才！天才！
Genius! Genius!
買収されたわ。
She got bribed.
買収された？
Bribed?
ギラギラ？
Gira gira?
ピカピカちょっと惜しくて、
Pika pika was pretty close,
それがね、ビカビカとかだったら正解。
but if it were "bika bika", it'd be correct.
あー！ビカビカ！
Ah! Bika bika!
もっと無理無理。
Even more impossible.
ビカが眩しいね。
"Bika" sounds dazzling, yeah.
あー、ビカビカの方が強いんだ。
Ah, bika bika is stronger.
そう。ピカピカはまあ、きらきらと同じくらいかな？
Yeah. Pika pika is about the same level as kirakira.
同じ？
The same?
ええー！
Ehhh?!
なるほど。
I see.
ちょっと弱いかな。ビカビカ、ギラギラ。
It's a bit weaker. Bika bika, gira gira.
Oh, so pika pika is on the same level as kira kira.
うん。
Yeah.
なんかいつも聞いてるのが、なんか「ギラギラ太陽なんとか」っていうのは...
What I always hear is like, "the glaring (gira gira) sun something"...
あ、そうそうそう！
Ah, yeah, yeah, yeah!
あ、そう！
Ah, right!
むねちのね、あのギラファもね
Munechi's "Girafarig" too,
あー、ギラファ！ギラギラ
Ah, Girafarig! Gira gira...
ファンミーティング、ギラファ。
Fan meeting, Giraffa.
とかもね。同じ感じで、明るい、眩しいみたいな。
That kind of thing too. In the same sense: bright, dazzling.
言葉かなと思いますね。
I think that's the nuance.
面白い。
Interesting.
I see, I see, I see. Now you know.
Bribing works?
Bribing works? I mean, I could bribe her.
Yeah, that works.
Okay, nice nice, nice info.
じゃあ続いていきましょう。
Alright, let's move on.
続いて、同じ感じでございますけども、
Next, in the same way,
心臓のこの音、「どきどき」を
this sound of the heart: "doki doki"...
もっと強く表現すると？
How would you express it more strongly?
A stronger doki doki!
ドキドキ！
Doki doki!
あれ？
Huh?
Bigger than doki doki?
どき...あれ？
Doki... huh?
これも何パターンかあるから、
There are multiple patterns for this too,
合ってたら大丈夫です。
so as long as it's right, it's fine.
何パターンかあるんだろうな。
I bet there are several patterns.
はい。
Yes.
どっちでもいいって感じですか、そしたら？
So any of them is fine then?
うん。まあ、2つ3つくらい表現はあるかな？
Yeah. Well, there are about 2 or 3 expressions.
えー
Hmm...
なんだろう？
What could it be?
ドキドキ... うん。
Doki doki... yeah.
んー、ドキドキねー。
Hmm, doki doki...
ドキドキ、ドキドキ...
Doki doki, doki doki...
どき...
Doki...
ドキドキ
Doki doki
ドキドキ...
Doki doki...
ドキより強く、強く。
Stronger than doki, stronger.
強く？
Stronger?
うん。
Yeah.
ドキドキが...
Doki doki is...
ちなみに弱くすると、
By the way, if you make it weaker,
うん、まあ、弱くすると「とくん、とくん」とかですね。
yeah, well, weaker would be like "tokun, tokun".
ほー / あー
Ohh / Ahh
おっ、オッケー。
Oh, okay.
これもちょっとヒントになるかな？
Maybe this will serve as a hint?
トクン、トクン、ドキドキ...
Tokun, tokun, doki doki...
Next...
Another like similar level is tokun tokun, so that's a hint.
So you want something stronger than tokun tokun.
Oh...
あ、これも、ちょっと可愛い声で「まつり先輩... あ、まつりお姉さん」って言ったらもっとヒントくれます？
Ah, for this too, if I say "Matsuri-senpai... ah, Matsuri Onee-san" in a cute voice, will you give more hints?
ヒント？！
Hints?!
ヒントくれます？
Will you give hints?
可愛く「まつりお姉さん」って言ったら、ヒントもっとくれます？
If I say "Matsuri Onee-san" cutely, will you give more hints?
あー、オッケー、オッケー。
Ah, okay, okay.
いいよ。どうぞ。
Sure. Go ahead.
え、い、いいんですか？
Eh, r-really? Is it okay?
いいよ。
Sure.
え、いいんですか？
Eh, is it okay?
うん。
Yeah.
まつりお姉...
Matsuri Onee...
ねぇちゃん、ちょっとあの、ヒントをお願いします。
Big sis, please give them a little hint.
しょうがないにゃあ。
Guess I have no choice, nya~
1つだけでいいから、おねえちゃん！
Just one is fine, big sis!
オーマイガー
Oh my god.
めっちゃこれヒントだけど...
This is a huge hint, but...
あー、まあ、強調するのに...
Ah, well, to emphasize it...
日本では結構小さい「っ」を入れたりとか...
in Japan, they often add a small "tsu"...
あ！あ！
Ah! Ah!
ドロドロです！
Doro-doro!
そうですね。
That's right.
あと言葉を変えるんだったら、あのー、なんだろ、なんだろうな...
Also, if you're changing the word, um... what would it be...
大きな、大きな音っぽいというか...
Like a louder, bigger sound, I guess...
まあ、ドームね、大きそうだけどね。
Well, a "dome" sounds pretty big though.
はい。ま、そんな感じですかね。
Yes. Well, something like that.
はい！ありがとう姉ちゃん！
Okay! Thank you, big sis!
うぉっ！
Whoa!
よし。
All right.
オッケー、オッケー、オッケー。
Okay, okay, okay.
Yeah, yeah, you could totally bribe the MC.
Okay!
じゃあ、聞いていきましょう。
Then let's hear them out.
Why didn't you bribe me, MC?
I would have let you win!
じゃあ、えー、イオフィって、いきますか？
Now then, uh, shall we start with Iofi?
はい！「ドックン」です！はい、「ドックン」！
Yes! It's "Dokkun"! Yes, "Dokkun"!
ドックン、ドックン。
Dokkun, dokkun.
はい！
Yes!
えー、じゃあ、こぼ！
Uh, next up, Kobo!
Uh, I remembered to mock Zeta about...
...a part of her original song lyrics.
It's "bagu bagu", but it's actually "baku-bagu" or...
..."baku-baku"...
Yeah, something like that.
ああー、「バクバク」ね。「バクバク」。うんうんうん。
Ah, "baku-baku," right. "Baku-baku." Mm-mm.
じゃあ、続いてアーニャ？
Then next up, Anya?
えー、ウマ娘。ズキ！ドキュン！ドキュン！
Um, Uma Musume. Zuki! Dokyun! Dokyun!
あ、ドキュンもある！
Ah, "dokyun" works too!
あーー！
Ahhh!
はい！はいはいはい。なるほど、確かに。
Yes! Yes, yes, yes. I see, indeed.
じゃあ、べーちゃん！
Then, Bae-chan!
いや、もう「どきどき」をもっと強くして、もはや心臓破裂。
No, I made "dokidoki" even stronger, so it's practically a heart rupture.
ドッ・ドドドドドドドド！
Do-dododododododo!
They're having a heart attack.
心臓ドドドドドドドになっちゃう。
Their heart turns into "dodododododo."
はい。じゃあ、ラオーラ！
Yes. Then, Raora!
It's uh... bakun bakun!
あー、「バクンバクン」！
Ah, "bakun bakun"!
Bakun bakun. Bakun bakun.
I was listening recently, so...
えー、あー、なるほどなるほど。
Ah, I see, I see.
...it must be it.
これ、結構みんな違うんだけどー、
Everyone's is quite different, but...
じゃ、正解...正解者は...
then the correct... who got it right is...
これね、全員正解でいいかなと思います！
I think everyone being correct is good here!
Oh, everyone's right! Yeah, everyone's right!
おおーー！
Ooh!
We're all winners!
結構いろんな表現があって、
There are actually a lot of different expressions,
へぇーー。
Ehh~.
まー、「ドッキン」とか、「ドックンドックン」とか...
well, like "dokkin", or "dokkun dokkun"...
うん、「どきどき」...「ドッキドキ」とか？
yeah, "dokidoki"... "dokkidoki"?
あとウキウキね。
And "ukiuki".
うん、特には、まー、「ドドドドドド」も強そうだし...
Yeah, especially, well, "dododododo" sounds strong too...
もう死んでるよ！
They're already dead!
死んでる？！
Dead?!
緊張、緊張してる時とかに「ドドドドドドー」って、表現されたりとか。
When you're tense or nervous, it's expressed as "dodododododo"...
あーー、はいはいはい。
Ahhh, right, right, right.
はい、ということで、全員正解！素晴らしい！
Yes, and with that, everyone is correct! Wonderful!
イエーイ！やったー！
Yay! We did it!
みんな正解！
Everyone got it right!
みんな上手！上手！
Everyone's so good! So good!
今度は、今からとあるサウンドを聴いてもらいます。
Next, I'm going to have you listen to a certain sound.
あの、チャンネルにね、ボイスを貼りますので...
Um, I'll post the voice clip in the channel, so...
これ、何て言っているんでしょうか？という問題でございますね。
The question is, "What is it saying?"
何を言って...いる？どういうこと？
What is it... saying? What do you mean?
何と聞こえるか。
What it sounds like.
今からセミの鳴き声を送ります。
I'm sending the cry of a cicada now.
うん、何と言っているでしょうか、セミは。
Yep, what is the cicada saying?
Alright, they've sent... she sent a little voice clip.
What is this cicada saying in the voice clip?
Okay.
じゃあ、ちょっとリスナーさんにも聴かせます。こちらです。
Then, let's let the listeners hear it too. Here it is.
Oh, so we have to come up with the onomatopoeia. なるほどね。
Oh, so we have to come up with the onomatopoeia. I see.
From listening to it?
Wait, is it there?
It's in the chat. In the chat.
はい。これは何と...
Yes. What is this...
なるほど、なるほど。
I see, I see.
ははははは。
Hahaha.
So what is that sound that the cicada is making?
日本人だったらね、絶対にわかるね。
If you're Japanese, you'd definitely know.
Cicada... So how do you draw chitchi... How do you pronounce it?
Cicada.
Cicada? Cicada. Cicada.
Cicada. Cicada, probably.
It's cicada? I always call it "chichada".
Chichada?!
Enchilada.
I don't know how to pronounce it!
I thought it was chichada.
これは何かなどれかな？
What could this be?
What does it look like?
Cicadas?
Cicadas. Cicadas.
おおー、わかるかな？
Ooh, I wonder if they know?
It has big wings.
Yeah.
見たこと...
Have you ever seen...
I'm pretty sure I never seen it before.
I'm pretty sure I've never seen it before.
I see it all the time inside...
here?
セミ...
Cicadas...
Yeah.
They're like everywhere.
They fall and they cannot fly again and they die quickly.
これ勝ったら...
If you get this right...
JPやね。
it's definitely JP.
さすがに。
No doubt.
セミ...
Cicadas...
本物のセミ見たことないんですか？
You've never seen a real cicada before?
え？
Huh?
え、いないの？
Huh, they don't have them?
いや、いるとは思うんだけど、
No, I think they exist,
声は聞こえるけど、姿が...なんかどこにいるのか分かんない。
but while you hear them, you don't know where they actually are.
そうなんだ。え、子供の頃セミ捕りとかしないの？
Really? Didn't you guys go cicada catching as kids?
ない。
Never.
ほー。
Wow.
あれは多分...結構なんか日本文化的なことなんだよね。
That's probably... pretty much a Japanese culture thing.
へー、そうなんだー。
Oh, really?
ないない。
Never done it.
セミの種類とか言われてもあんま分かんないのか。
So even if someone mentions cicada species, you wouldn't know?
分かんない。全員セミだもん。
No idea. They're all just cicadas.
全員セミだもん。
They're all just cicadas.
へー。
Wow.
そうなんだ。
I see.
Alright, you're... Anyone of you guys caught cicadas before?
Alright, you're... Have any of you guys caught cicadas before?
Cicadas, Bear, cicada, cicada... Ever caught one before?
Cicadas, Bae, cicada, cicada... Ever caught one before?
No.
No, not a cicada.
I found one in my balcony.
I found one on my balcony.
え？In your balcony?
Huh? On your balcony?
Yeah.
It was huge. It was like super big.
倒れてるやつ？
A fallen one?
And it was super loud.
バルコニー？
Balcony?
ベランダ、ベランダにゃ。
Veranda, veranda.
ベランダね。
Veranda, right.
ベランダにいた？
It was on the veranda?
へー！そんなに大きいの？セミって。
Really? Are cicadas that big?
セミ
Cicadas.
結構でかいよ。よくいるよ、そのへんに死んでたりとか。
They're pretty big. They're often lying around dead nearby.
マジ？
Really?
Big bug.
こぼは大丈夫だったかな？
Were you okay, Kobo?
大丈夫くない。
I'm not okay.
大丈夫くない？何回も聞いていいよ。
Not okay? You can listen to it multiple times.
大丈夫じゃない。
I'm not okay.
何回も。
Multiple times.
大丈夫じゃない。
I'm not okay.
Can I have hint?
Can I have a hint?
ヒントお願い。
Please give us a hint.
ヒント？ヒントはー...
A hint? The hint is...
なんかあの「ショワショワショワ」って言ってるのは無視していい。
You can ignore the background "shwa-shwa-shwa" sound.
その大きい低めの音の
It's about what the louder, lower-pitched
セミさんは何て言ってるかだね。
cicada is buzzing like.
Oh.
Focus on the lower-sounding notes. Ignore the "shwa shwa shwa shwa" in the background.
困ってるねー。
You guys are struggling!
オッケー？オッケー？
Okay? Ready?
じゃあ行きましょう。よぴぴから。
Let's go, starting with Yopipi.
はい。「みーんみん」でな... はいはい、「みーんみん」
Yes! With "min min"... Yes, yes, "min min".
はい、「みーん」ね。オッケー。
Alright, "min", okay.
じゃあこぼちゃん。
Next, Kobo-chan.
「ちー」
"Chiー"
「ちー」かわいい！
"Chiー", so cute!
「ちー」
"Chiー"
オッケーオッケー、「ちー」だね。
Okay, okay, "chiー", right.
「ちー」だね。かわいい。
"Chiー", right. Cute!
はい。じゃあジジ。
Okay, next, Gigi (Zeta).
ジジは「じーじーじー」
Gigi's is "Jii-jii-jii".
ジジの鳴き声！
That's Gigi's own cry!
ジジの鳴き声。
Gigi's cry.
おー。じゃあ続いてべっちゃん。
Oh. Next is Bae-chan.
えー、「ういーん」
Uh, "Ween".
「ういーん」
"Ween".
「ういーん」ね。オッケーオッケー。
"Ween", okay, okay.
じゃあラスト、ララ。
Next, last one, Rara (Anya).
あ、えっと、「くりくりくり」
Ah, um, "Kuri kuri kuri".
かわいい！「くりくり」
Cute! "Kuri kuri".
オッケーオッケー。
Okay, okay.
じゃあ正解行きましょう。
Now then, let's see the correct answer.
正解は... はい！
The answer is... here!
「みーんみんみんみん」で...
"Min min min min", so...
よぴぴ正解！
Yopipi is correct!
やったー！
Yay!
It doesn't sound like "min" at all!
How is that Japanese?!
ちょっと聞こえないんだよね。「M」。「M」の音なくない？
You really can't hear "M". Isn't there no "M" sound?
There's no "M" sound!
このセミの名前がそもそも「ミンミンゼミ」というね、名前のセミで。
The name of this cicada is actually "Minminzemi" in Japanese.
あー！ミンミンゼミ！
Ah! Minminzemi!
「みーんみんみん」って日本人には聞こえてますね。
To Japanese ears, it sounds like "min-min-min".
そうなんだ。はい。
I see. Yes.
へー。
Heh.
じゃあ続いて、ネクストセミいきますよ。
Now then, moving on to the next cicada!
ネクストセミ？
Next cicada?
Is cicada sound?
Is that a cicada sound?
Nice voice!
Here we go.
ワンモアセミいきます。
Here goes one more cicada.
One more semi. Okay.
One more cicada. Okay.
はい、ワンモアセミ。「セミツー」こちらです。
Yes, one more cicada. Here is "Cicada 2".
じゃあ皆さんにも聞かせます。
Let's play it for everyone.
ほい。
Here.
セミツー！
Cicada 2!
あれ？
Huh?
まだなーい！
Not yet!
なんじゃこれ？！
What is this?!
What is happening?
何？
What?
はいはい、めっちゃ聞こえますね。多分日本人にはめちゃめちゃ...
Yes, yes, you hear it clearly. Probably to Japanese people, it's super...
へー。
Oh...
...聞こえる。
...obvious.
What's the sound from?
Where's the sound from?
え？
Huh?
I don't know.
What the heck?
セミバージョン2ですよ。
It's Cicada Version 2!
へー。
Hmm.
分かるかな？
Can you tell?
セミ2ね？
Cicada 2, right?
セミツー。
Cicada 2.
ヒントをお願いします。
Please give us a hint!
ヒント？
A hint?
ヒントはー...
The hint is...
ヒントは...
あの、「タタタタターン、タタタタターン」っていうのが鳴き声。
That "ta-ta-ta-ta-taan, ta-ta-ta-ta-taan" is its call.
タタタタターン？／タタタタターン...
Ta-ta-ta-ta-taan? / Ta-ta-ta-ta-taan...
が、日本人には...
But to Japanese people...
「タタタタターン」、だからまあ5文字くらいかな？
"Ta-ta-ta-ta-taan", so about five letters or so?
ん？ 5？／タタタタ...
Huh? Five? / Ta-ta-ta-ta...
Pick a sound that makes that pattern.
Pattern?
A pattern?
ヒント難しいね、これは。
Giving hints for this is hard.
ヒントとしてはムズいな。
As a hint, that's really tough.
「タタタタターン」もオノマトペやろって言われたら、もうごめんなさい、それは。
If you say "ta-ta-ta-ta-taan" is an onomatopoeia too, then I'm sorry.
えー、ムズ。
Man, that's hard.
もうダダダダダダダダダしか思い出せない。
All I can think of is "da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da-da".
Hmm, maybe...
7文字だった！ ごめん、日本人には7文字。
It's seven letters! Sorry, to Japanese people it's seven.
まあ伸ばし棒が入ります、あと。最後のほうに。
Also, there's a prolonged sound mark near the end.
え？／There's an elongated...
Huh? / There's an elongated...
え、7文字？／伸ばす？／There's an elongated sound.
Seven letters? / Prolonged? / There's an elongated sound.
伸ばすと7文字ですね。
If you count the dash, it's seven characters.
えー...
Eh...
何やろ？ 「アゲハ」流しとくか。
What is it? Should I just write "Ageha"?
難しいね。／ムズい。
It's difficult. / Tough.
リズム自体はわかるんだけど、どう書いていいのかわからない。
I know the rhythm itself, but I don't know how to write it.
落ち着くね。
It's relaxing.
トトトトトトーン、ドドドドーンね。
Like "to-to-to-to-to-to-toan, do-do-do-doan", right?
落ち着く？
Relaxing?
この声を聞くと落ち着きますよ、「夏だな」って。
Hearing this sound relaxes you, thinking "Ah, it's summer."
ええ？
Huh?
Apparently the sound is relaxing to the Japanese.
ええ？
What?
落ち着くよね。
It's relaxing, right?
Okay.
じゃあ行きましょうか。よぴぴから。
Alright, let's go. Starting with Yopipi.
いや、「ククククククク」じゃないですか？ セミバージョン2。
Isn't it "ku-ku-ku-ku-ku-ku-ku"? Cicada version 2.
セミバージョン2？ セミバージョン2って何？
Cicada version 2? What's cicada version 2?
クククククッね。／クククククッで。
"Ku-ku-ku-ku-ku", right. / "Ku-ku-ku-ku-ku".
おー。／オーイ。
Ooh. / All right.
オッケーオッケー。じゃあこぼちゃん。
Okay, okay. Next, Kobo-chan.
Um... so...
The previous one was "ming-ming", right?
And uh I heard this is more than "ming-ming",
so it's a mating call like "meng-meng-meng-meng"!
ちょっと待って。
Wait a minute.
そもそも、why did you write "Mating Call"?
In the first place, why did you write "Mating Call"?
ええと、求愛の鳴き声、「メンメン」です。
Um, a mating call: "meng-meng".
ああー。でも求愛の鳴き声なんだよね、実際。
Ah. But it actually is a mating call.
あ、そうなの！？／So yes!
Oh, really?! / So yes!
Wait, it is a mating call?!
It is! Oh my god, I won! I'm right!
セミのオスがあの、「メス来てー」って言ってるときの声だから、そこは正しい。
It's the sound of male cicadas calling out for females, so that part is right.
へえー！
Wow!
求愛ですね。
It's a courtship call.
Oh my god.／「Oh my god」コールだ！
Oh my god. / It's the "Oh my god" call!
でも「メンメン」が正しいかどうかね。
But whether "meng-meng" is correct or not...
Ah so "meng-meng", ne? Okay.／Whether it's "meng-meng" or not.
Ah, so "meng-meng", right? Okay. / Whether it's "meng-meng" or not.
オーイ。続いてジジ。
All right. Next is Gigi.
Um... td-d-d-d-JEET... td-d-d-d-JEET... td-d-d-d-JEET...
...JEET!
はい、オッケー。「トゥルルル・ジー」オッケーね。
Yes, okay. "Trrr-Jii", okay.
オッケー。じゃあべちゃ。
Okay. Next is Becha.
え？ なんか...「ポコポコピカァ！ ポコポコピカァ！」
Huh? Like... "Poko poko pikaa! Poko poko pikaa!"
ポケモンっぽかったんだけど。／ポケモン？ ポケモンみたい。
It sounded like a Pokemon. / Pokemon? Like a Pokemon.
オッケー。「ポコポコピカァ」、オッケー。
Okay. "Poko poko pikaa", okay.
じゃあラオーラ。
Next is Raora.
Ah...
In my opinion, it's a cricket,
and a cricket sounds like "pring-pring-pring-pring".
プリンプリン、かわいい。／プリンプリンね、プリンプリン。
"Pring-pring", cute. / "Pring-pring", right? "Pring-pring".
プリンプリン、オッケーオッケー。
"Pring-pring", okay, okay.
You think it's a cricket. Like cricket.
じゃあ行きます。こちらの鳴き声は...
Alright, here we go. This call is...
「ツクツクボウシ」でございます！
"Tsukutsukuboushi"!
えええー！？／はいー！？
Ehhhh?! / What?!
な、な、なぜ？ なんで？ なんで？
W-W-Why? Why? Why?
ツクツクボーイズ、ツクツクボーイズ...
"Tsukutsuku-boys, tsukutsuku-boys..."
ツクツクボース！
Tsukutsukuboushi!
Boys?!／ツクツクボース！
Boys?! / Tsukutsukuboushi!
So I should do this if I want to mating call someone?
違います！ 違います！
No! No!
Did you say...／Can you flirt like that?
Did you say... / Can you flirt like that?
もっとジジ、もっとジジ求愛の鳴き声...
No, Gigi, a real mating call is...
ボッシュ！ ツクツクボッシュ！
Boushi! Tsukutsukuboushi!
やばいやばいやばい！
Oh no, oh no, oh no!
やばい！／Shut up, please!
Oh no! / Shut up, please!
学んでしまった。
She learned something bad.
シャラップお願いシャラップ！
Shut up, please, shut up!
はい。まあ「ツクツクボウシ」か「ツクツクホウシ」、どっちでもオッケー。
Yes. Well, either "Tsukutsukuboushi" or "Tsukutsukuhoushi" is okay.
ツクツクホウシ？／どっちでもオッケーで。
Tsukutsukuhoushi? / Either one is fine.
へえー、ツクツクボース。／となっております。
Huh, Tsukutsukuboushi. / That is the answer.
はい。ちょっとね、これセミは難しいですねー。
Yes. Cicadas are a bit tricky, aren't they?
Wow.
へえー、セミの種類とかは関係ないんですか？
Huh, so the species of cicada doesn't matter?
あ、これは「ツクツクボウシ」っていうセミの鳴き声ですね、今のは。
Oh, this one was the call of a cicada species called "Tsukutsukuboushi".
あ、種類？
Oh, the species?
そう、種類も「ツクツクボウシ」っていう名前のセミ。
Yes, the species itself is a cicada named "Tsukutsukuboushi".
へえー。
Huh.
ちなみに他にも、さっきのがミンミンゼミだったでしょ？
By the way, the previous one was the Minminzemi, right?
アブラゼミっていうのが、あのジジがさっき言ってた「ジジジジジジジ」って鳴くのがアブラ...
And the Aburazemi is the one that cries "Ji-ji-ji-ji-ji" like Gigi said earlier...
セミだったり
...like cicadas.
アブラゼミ。/ アブラゼミ、はい。
A large brown cicada. / A large brown cicada, yes.
日本人だったら...
If you're Japanese...
セミの声を聞くだけで、何のセミか分かります。
just by hearing a cicada chirp, you can tell what kind it is.
えー！ Wow! / Wow.
Huh?! / Wow! / Wow.
They can differentiate what kind of...
...cicada it is depending on what it sounds like?
There's different enchiladas?
Enchila— Yeah, so what we heard were two different enchiladas, Gigi.
So you're saying that there is an enchilada that says "ji-ji"?
Yeah, there is. / Yeah, there is.
え、3種類って何の名前だったっけ？
Wait, what were the names of those 3 kinds?
えーと、「ジジジ」はアブラゼミですね。
Um, "ji-ji-ji" is the large brown cicada.
アブラゼミ！ / はい。
Aburazemi! / Yes.
アブラゼミ... / 茶色のやつ？
Aburazemi... / The brown one?
アブラゼミ... / アブラゼミ。/ Yes.
Aburazemi... / Aburazemi. / Yes.
アブラゼミ、はい。/ After together?
Aburazemi, yes. / After together?
A large brown cicada. Mm.
はい。/ Large brown cicada goes...
Yes. / Large brown cicada goes...
なるほど！ なるほど！
I see! I see!
なるほど！ / なるほど！ なるほど。
I see! / I see! I see.
続いてラスト問題！
Moving on to the last question!
ラスト！ / ラスト！ / ラスト！
Last! / Last! / Last!
これはめっちゃちょっと、ジャパニーズすぎる...
This is very... a bit too Japanese...
難しいと思うんですけど...
and might be difficult, but...
これ解けたらもう... / 難しい？ オッケー。
If you can solve this... / Difficult? Okay.
いつ日本に来ても戦えます。
you can handle yourself anytime you visit Japan.
戦える？
We can handle it?
戦える。オッケー。
You can. Okay.
日本には独特な...
In Japan, there is a unique...
これにしか使わないオノマトペがあります。
onomatopoeia used only for this.
桃が川から流れてくる...
What is the onomatopoeia for...
オノマトペは何でしょう？
a peach floating down the river?
What is the onomatopoeia for when...
...a peach comes flowing down the river?
A peach? / 桃太郎読んだことないんだったら...
A peach? / If you've never read Momotaro...
桃太郎読んでねぇ！ / 読んだことないんだったら出来ないじゃないですか、これ、桃太郎。
Read Momotaro! / If you haven't read it, you won't be able to do this! It's Momotaro!
これ分かったらもう日本に来ていただいていつでも。
If you know this, you're ready to visit Japan anytime.
So, what is the sound...
...that a peach makes when it flows down the river?
It's a very, very specific onomatopoeia.
I'm guessing if you know the story of Momotaro...
Oh! / 字が汚いよ。
Oh! / My handwriting is so messy.
Is it folklore?
Yeah, you know the one with the Peach Boy? The Momotaro? Peach Boy? / Oh!
Yeah, it's very specific.
えー、分かんない。 / We gotta guess, we gotta guess, we gotta guess!
Um, I don't know. / We gotta guess, we gotta guess, we gotta guess!
桃にしか使わないですね。
It's only used for peaches.
リンゴとかが川に流れてても使わない。
Even if an apple is floating down a river, you wouldn't use it.
えー？ / Only used for peaches?
Eh? / Only used for peaches?
It's only peaches. / Oh, my God.
No, I'm sure this is gonna be really weird.
これ桃太郎読んでないと分かんないやつ。
This is something you won't know unless you've read Momotaro.
いや、桃太郎1回読んだんだよね。/ お、じゃあ分かるじゃん。
No, I read Momotaro once. / Oh, then you should know it!
Maybe I know that legend, but ah, 'cause I've watched...
And if you read the actual book, it's written in the actual book, like in Japanese.
So if you haven't read it, then you probably don't know.
I have no clue!
なんか確か前にあの雑談配信でこれのことちょっと語った気がする。
I feel like I talked about this during a chit-chat stream before.
そうなんだ！
Is that so!
そう、何でこうなったのって言われたら分かんないけど。
Yeah, though if you ask me why it became that way, I wouldn't know.
え、すごいねでも。話すんだ。
Wow, that's amazing though. You talk about that?
昔話ね。
Folktales, yeah.
はい。
Yeah.
何だっけ？
What was it again?
これはね、たぶん知らないと本当に当てられないと思うけど...
This one, if you don't already know it, you probably really won't guess it, but...
日本人だったら、あの小さい子からおじいちゃんおばあちゃんまでみんな分かるからね。
if you're Japanese, everyone from little kids to grandpas and grandmas knows it.
桃の川流れてる音なんだって。
Apparently it's the sound of a peach flowing down a river.
Oh...
はい、じゃあ行きましょうか、最終問題。じゃあ、よぴちどうでしょう？
Alright, let's check the final question. So Yopichi, what is your answer?
はい、「どんぶらっこ」です。
Yes, it's "donburakko".
はい、「どんぶらっこ」。「どんぶらこ」、オッケー！
Yes, "donburakko". "Donburako", okay!
じゃあ、こぼちゃん。/ はい。
Next, Kobo-chan. / Yes.
お尻？
A butt?
モンゴモンゴー
Mongo mongo!
モンゴモンゴー！ / Mongo Mongo!
Mongo mongo! / Mongo Mongo!
可愛い。
Cute.
お尻みたい、流れてるの。/ はい。
It looks like a butt floating. / Yes.
うん。お尻みたいね。/ じゃあ、ジジ！
Yeah. Looks like a butt, right? / Alright, Gigi!
Um, if I saw a huge peach floating in the water...
...and it was like a really big peach and it was huge, and you know, like a peach, I would go:
"Ah, wa! Dekai!"
"Ah, whoa! It's huge!"
めちゃめちゃジューシー！ でかい！
Super juicy! Huge!
ジューシー！ / おばあちゃん... / ジューシー！ でかい！
Juicy! / Grandma... / Juicy! Huge!
でかいのね。/ でかい！ / そういうの「でかっ！」ってなっちゃうのね。
It's huge, right? / Huge! / In that case, you just go "huge!", right?
お尻でかい！ / お尻でかい！
Huge butt! / Huge butt!
ヤバい！ ヤバい！ / でかいね、はい。
Oh boy! Oh boy! / It's huge, yes.
じゃあ、べーちゃん。
Next, Bae-chan.
なんか、「どんぴしゃっ！」
Kind of like "donpisha!"
っていう音。/ 「どんぴしゃ」？ / 「どんぴしゃっ！」
...that kind of sound. / "Donpisha"? / "Donpisha!"
水のね。水の... / 水の音ね。/ 「どんびしゃ」ね。
The water, right? The water's... / The sound of water. / "Donbisha", yeah.
「どんびしゃ」 / はい。/ 「どんびしゃ」
Donbisha. / Yes. / Donbisha.
じゃあ、続いてラオーラ。
Alright, next up, Raora.
Uh, maybe it's "puka puka"?
あ、「プカプカ」！ / プカプカ！ かわいい！ / プカプカ
Ah, "pukapuka"! / Pukapuka! Cute! / Pukapuka.
「プカプカ」 / Maybe.
"Pukapuka". / Maybe.
オッケー！ じゃあ正解行きましょう！ 正解...
Okay! Let's reveal the correct answer! The answer...
あ
Ah
どんぶらこ、どんぶらこですね
It's "donburako, donburako."
どんぶらこ、どんぶらこ / Oh my god
Donburako, donburako. / Oh my god!
なぜです？
Why is that?
なぜかは、そうやって本に書いてあるからね。
As for why, that's just how it's written in the book.
あー / へー
Ah... / I see.
理由はない。
There is no reason.
え、ちなみに... / 理由はない？
By the way... / No reason?
ない、ない。ないよ。
None, none. There isn't any.
そう聞こえるのか
That's just how it sounds?
うん、そう。
Yeah, that's right.
で、あれだね、「プカプカ」は...
And, well, "puka-puka" is...
浮いてるもの？水に浮いてたら「プカプカ」で合ってる。
for something floating? If it's floating on water, "puka-puka" is correct.
So if it's floating in the water, it would be "puka-puka"?
Yeah, but if it's- 'cause it's coming down the stream, it's flowing down the stream...
Yeah, but if it's—'cause it's coming down the stream, it's flowing down the stream...
どんぶらこ、どんぶらこ
"Donburako, donburako."
そう、で、桃が川から流れてくる時は「どんぶらこ」ですね。
Right. So when a peach floats down a river, it's "donburako."
And it has to be a peach? If it's an apple or anything else, it's not...
じゃあリンゴだったら何？
Then what if it's an apple?
リンゴだったら「プカプカ」。
If it's an apple, it's "puka-puka."
Oh my god!
桃だけ！Peach only! どんぶらこ。
Peach only! "Peach only" is donburako.
なんでだろうな。/ Oh my god.
I wonder why. / Oh my god.
ということでね、えー皆さ...
So with that said, everyone...
Why, Japan?!
難しいよね、オノマトペ。
Onomatopoeia is difficult, isn't it?
でも可愛かったのでね。
But it was cute, so...
あ、で、ちなみにオノマトペではないんですけど、今日みんなにじゃあ覚えてってほしい言葉があります。
Ah, and by the way, it's not an onomatopoeia, but here's a word I'd like you all to learn today.
Oh, there's phrases that she wants us to learn. / 全然分からない
Oh, there's phrases that she wants us to learn. / "Not understanding at all"...
「全然分からない」っていうのを、日本語では「ちんぷんかんぷん」って言いますね。
To say "I don't understand at all," in Japanese we say "chinpunkanpun."
あー！/ ちんぷんかんぷん！かわいい！
Ah! / Chinpunkanpun! That's cute!
はい、ちんぷんかんぷん！/ プンプン？
Yes, chinpunkanpun! / Punpun?
ちんぷんかんぷん
Chinpunkanpun.
ちんぷんかんぷん！/ そうそうそう。
Chinpunkanpun! / Yes, yes, yes.
ちんぷんかんぷん
Chinpunkanpun.
これは全然分からない...
This means you don't understand at all...
When you have no idea of anything, this is the onomatopoeia you use.
ちんぷんかんぷん / オノマトペ
Chinpunkanpun. / Onomatopoeia.
I like that! / I'm very scared of you using this phrase, Gigi.
Every time someone asks me something: Chinpunkanpun!
I'm just scared of you forgetting what the full phrase is...
Chin- ch...
助かった言葉ですよ、日本語ちんぷんかんぷん。
It's a lifesaver phrase: "My Japanese is chinpunkanpun."
はい、ということで。
Yes, so moving on.
怖いな、なんか「ちんぷんかんぷん」っていうオノマトペを...
It's scary, if with the onomatopoeia "chinpunkanpun"...
全部ちょっと覚えられない時だったら...
she can't remember the full word...
ああ、「チン」がね。/ 忘れれば... / ね、ちょっと...
Ah, the "chin" part. / If you forget... / Yeah, that's a bit...
覚えられないジジがちょっと怖いんだよね！
Gigi not being able to remember it is what scares me!
覚えて、「ちんぷんかんぷん」。漢字もあるからね、「ちんぷんかんぷん」って。
Remember it: "chinpunkanpun." There are even kanji for "chinpunkanpun."
え、漢字もあるの？
Eh, there's kanji for it too?
そう、漢字もあります、「ちんぷん...」/ へぇ～
Yes, there are kanji for it. / Wow~
カタカナじゃない。カタカナで言ったりひらがなで言うことが多いけど、ちゃんとね、漢字がある。
It's not just katakana. It's usually written in katakana or hiragana, but it actually has kanji.
漢字が？/ そう、漢字があるんだ。/ あります。
Kanji? / Yes, there are kanji. / There are.
え、漢字あるの？/ はい。
Wait, there's kanji? / Yes.
なのでね... / ちんぷんかんぷん
So... / Chinpunkanpun.
むずっ！/ 読めん！/ むずっ！
So hard! / Can't read that! / So hard!
コメントでね、書いてくれてるけど、それが「珍紛漢紛」ですね。
Chat is writing it out—that's "珍紛漢紛" (chinpunkanpun).
珍しい... / 珍しい粉？
Rare... / Rare powder?
珍しい粉、何？漢字の「漢」、何とかほにゃららの「普」
Rare, powder, what? The "kan" of kanji, and whatever "pun"...
うん、「珍紛漢紛」ですね。
Yeah, "珍紛漢紛."
でもめっちゃ可愛いから、もし日本語分かんなくなったら、「日本語ちんぷんかんぷんです」って言ったらもうオッケー。全て解決。
But it's super cute, so if you don't understand Japanese, just say "My Japanese is chinpunkanpun," and you're good. Problem solved.
オッケー！/ オッケー！/ やった！/ オッケー！
Okay! / Okay! / Yay! / Okay!
はい、ということで。
Alright, moving right along.
I have one onomatopoeia that Okayu-senpai taught me once.
おっ、おかゆ先輩に教えてくれたオノマトペがあります。何ですか？
Oh, an onomatopoeia Okayu-senpai taught you. What is it?
え、ブルンブルンです！
Uh, it's "burun-burun"!
ブルンブルン？/ ブルンブルンは... / ブルンブルン？
Burun-burun? / "Burun-burun" is... / Burun-burun?
おっぱいを、おっぱいを揺らす時の音。
The sound of, the sound when shaking breasts.
Oh my! / ブルンブルン
Oh my! / Burun-burun.
え、ブルンブルン... / ボインボイン...
Eh, burun-burun... / Boin-boin...
あ、そう、ボインボインも合ってる。ボインボイン、ブルンブルン、オッケー。合ってる、両方おっぱい。
Ah, yeah, "boin-boin" is also right. Boin-boin, burun-burun, okay. Both are right, both for breasts.
で、もっと大きなオッパイだと「バインバイン」になります。
And for even bigger breasts, it becomes "bain-bain."
バインバイン？！/ もっと？！もっと大きなおっぱいはバインバイン！
Bain-bain?! / Even bigger?! Even bigger breasts are "bain-bain"!
それ以上大きな物はないですか？
Is there nothing bigger than that?
それ以上大きいのは無いね。多分「バインバイン」が一番大きい。/ なるほど。
There's nothing bigger than that. "Bain-bain" is probably the biggest. / I see.
はい、ということで。/ Japan, why?!
Alright, so with that... / Japan, why?!
最後これかい！じゃあ、えー...
That's what we end on?! Okay then, um...
今日の優勝者 一応発表しますか？
Shall we go ahead and announce today's winner?
今日はですね イオフィが優勝でございます もうほぼ…
Today's winner is... Iofi! Having gotten almost...
やったー！
Yay! I did it!
半分以上正解して…
...more than half of them right...
天才だ！
You're a genius!
流石でございます
As expected of her.
いやいや 日本語上手
No, no... / Your Japanese is so good!
日本語上手 でもね えっと他のメンバーも
Your Japanese is great. But you know, the other members...
あれですよ 半分は正解してますから 素晴らしいでございます
also answered half of them correctly, so that's wonderful too!
やったー！
Yay!
ということで 皆さん本日もありがとうございましたー！
And with that, thank you all so much for watching today!
え チャンネル登録もね
And please make sure to...
ありがとうございました！
Thank you so much! / Thank you!
センキュー！ じゃあチャンネル登録も…
Thank you! And also don't forget to subscribe to the—
あ ちょちょちょ…
Ah, wait, wait, wait...
チャンネル登録のほうも ポチッとお願いしますね
Please make sure to click that subscribe button!
お願いしまーす！
Please do!
ということで 最後はバイバイで終わっていきますよ せーの！
With that said, let's wrap it up with "bye-bye"! Ready, set...
バイバーイ！
Bye-bye!
ちんぷんかんぷん！ ちんぷんかんぷん！
Chimpunkanpun! Chimpunkanpun!
ぶろんぶろん！ バイバーイ！
Vroom vroom! Bye-bye!